Guide to the Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection ARC.002
Brooklyn Historical Society
Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection
Bulk, 1961-1971
1943-2007
ARC.002
Brooklyn Historical Society
13.75 Linear feet in 13 manuscript boxes, 5 record cartons, and 2 artifact boxes
The Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection consists principally of the subject files concerning 1960s civil rights activism maintained by Arnie Goldwag, an officer of Brooklyn CORE during the first half of the 1960s. These files include correspondence, newsletters, event announcements (e.g., fliers), directions for demonstrators, photographs, press releases, clippings, and other documents related to many of the actions conducted by Brooklyn CORE, particularly for the period 1961-1965. Actions represented in the collection include those protesting discrimination in employment, housing, schools, and the like, including the controversial initiative to block traffic in connection with the opening of the 1964 World's Fair. The collection also includes reminiscences by Goldwag and other CORE members looking back from the 1990s and 2000s. In addition to Brooklyn CORE-related material, the collection includes material related to other 1960s activist groups, including those involved with civil rights, Vietnam War opposition, and draft resistance, among others.
Committee for Peace Organization.
Congress of Racial Equality. Brooklyn Chapter.
Congress of Racial Equality.
End the Draft Committee.
Goldwag, Arnold
Arrangement note
The collection is organized in two series: Subject Files and Books.
Biographical/Historical note
Arnold (Arnie) Stanley Goldwag was born on January 18, 1938. A resident of Brooklyn, Goldwag attended Brooklyn College beginning in 1955 where he held leadership positions in a range of organizations, including social fraternities, student government, and student rights groups. He left Brooklyn College about 1961 without graduating, though he was readmitted in 1966 and graduated in 1968.
While still at Brooklyn College in the late 1950s, Goldwag became involved in the activities of the Brooklyn chapter of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), starting with distributing fliers urging a boycott of Woolworth's. His role in the chapter expanded quickly, and in the years of Goldwag's active participation in CORE (1960-1965), he held leadership positions, principally as the Community Relations Director. In this position, Goldwag was responsible for press relations, publicity, and coordination with communities and demonstrators on the organization's direct actions. Over the course of his tenure in Brooklyn CORE, Goldwag participated in a number of actions, both locally, such as the 1963 Board of Education sit-in, and nationally, such as in Cambridge, Maryland, where Goldwag was involved in CORE's effort to desegregate public facilities. Goldwag's activism led to several arrests and a 13 month prison sentence in 1964; he served one month of the sentence in Rikers Island penitentiary.
Founded in Chicago in 1942, CORE was centered on the principles of interracial, nonviolent direct action. Local chapters that affiliated with national CORE had a great deal of autonomy of action. Within this structure, Brooklyn CORE emerged in the early 1960s as one of the most radical CORE chapters, focusing on the living conditions of poor African-Americans in Bedford-Stuyvesant and employing increasingly aggressive confrontational tactics. It was during this surging radical activism in Brooklyn CORE that Goldwag was a central figure in the chapter and in its many civil rights actions. Indeed, Goldwag was a principal creator of one of Brooklyn CORE's most controversial actions, the Stall-In at the opening of the 1964 World's Fair. This action, which called for the deliberate blockage of automobile traffic headed to the Fair in order to call attention to discrimination against African-Americans, led to the suspension of the chapter by CORE.
Subsequent to his days with CORE, which ended in 1965, and his 1968 graduation from Brooklyn College, Goldwag went to work for the New York City Human Resources Administration as a contract manager for home care programs. In the 1990s he went on leave to work for his union (Social Service Employees Union Local 371) as Health and Safety Coordinator. In the 1990s and 2000s, Goldwag was actively engaged in ensuring that the civil rights movement was remembered, and its continued struggle recognized. He participated in a number of conferences and oral histories, and opened his files to researchers. Arnie Goldwag died on August 9, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The bulk of the collection was donated to the Brooklyn Historical Society in 2009 by Gilda Goldwag, the wife of the late Arnie Goldwag. A second donation of some additional correspondence was made by Ms. Goldwag in 2010.
Related Archival Materials note
At Brooklyn Historical Society:
Brooklyn Historical Society holds fifteen slides made by Oliver Lewis of photographs credited to Bob Adelman which concern CORE actions circa 1962, including protests at the Board of Education. These are available for viewing in the library's PastPerfect database (accession V1989.22).
The BHS library also holds some books about CORE, other than those in the Goldwag collection itself. These can be found through the on-line Bobcat catalog, searching on the term "Congress of Racial Equality."
Other than Brooklyn Historical Society:
The Brooklyn Collection of Brooklyn Public Library (BPL) holds Dr. Brian Purnell's Ph.D. thesis: A movement grows in Brooklyn: the Brooklyn chapter of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) and the northern civil rights movement during the early 1960's. BPL also holds various oral histories and transcripts conducted by Dr. Purnell during his research.
In addition, BPL holds materials donated by Rioghan Kirchner, another important leader of Brooklyn CORE. There are photos, news clippings, some case files from housing investigations, and materials that pertain to FOCUS, a Brooklyn-based housing advocacy organization Kirchner helped found after her time in Brooklyn CORE. And BPL holds nearly the entire collection (1969-1983) of Black News, the major publication of The East, a black nationalist organization.
Columbia University's Oral History Office holds three tapes of interviews with Arnie Goldwag. According to the webpage of oral historian Sheila B. Williams (http://www.crmvet.org/nars/orallist.htm), interviews that she conducted in 1999 and 2001 with Goldwag "discuss [the] founding [and] functions of Brooklyn CORE. Last tape also discusses the Route 40 campaign [and] his friendship with Stokely Carmichael (Kwame Ture), including Stokely's last days [and] death upon returning to New York." Ms. Williams's oral histories also include one from 2000 with Elaine Bibuld, a Brooklyn CORE activist who was at the center of certain of the actions prominent in BHS's Goldwag collection.
Wisconsin Historical Society holds two archival boxes of Brooklyn CORE records collected by Oliver and Marjorie Leeds, officers of the chapter during the 1960s ( Register of the Congress of Racial Equality. Brooklyn Chapter: Records, 1959-1978; Mss 947.) An on-line finding aid is available and can be found through WHS's catalog at http://arcat.library.wisc.edu/.
Wisconsin Historical Society is the principal repository holding national CORE's papers. These are also available on microform, which is available at the Schomburg. Schomburg also holds other material related to CORE. Again, use search term "Congress of Racial Equality."
Scope and Contents
The Arnie Goldwag Brooklyn Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) collection consists principally of the subject files concerning 1960s civil rights activism maintained by Arnie Goldwag, an officer of Brooklyn CORE during the first half of the 1960s. These files include correspondence, newsletters, event announcements (e.g., fliers), directions for demonstrators, photographs, press releases, clippings, and other documents related to many of the actions conducted by Brooklyn CORE, particularly for the period 1961-1965. Actions represented in the collection include those protesting discrimination in employment, housing, local government services, schools, and the like. The collection includes actions, such as the Stall-In at the 1964 World's Fair, aimed at calling attention to discrimination practiced in Brooklyn and in the metropolitan New York City area, as well as participation in nationally-oriented initiatives, such as the 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom.
While the collection documents Brooklyn CORE's actions as an organization, it also documents the intersection of activism with the life of an important activist, Arnie Goldwag. The collection includes documentation of Goldwag's student years at Brooklyn College, his military draft status, arrest records, correspondence written to him while in Rikers Island prison, his reflections on his CORE activism, and other material. In addition, personal correspondence to Goldwag from other former CORE activists often include reflections on their activism.
The collection holds little or no material on CORE from the years after 1965, and little material generally from the 1970s and 1980s. Nevertheless, the collection holds material from the 1980s-2000s that concern reunions, memorials, reminiscences, research papers, and other reflections on CORE, the civil rights struggle, and its continuing legacy.
In addition to Brooklyn CORE, there is material in the collection from other national and New York organizations concerned with civil rights actions, including the Student NonViolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and Harlem Parents Committee, among others. There is also material from the mid to late 1960s concerning anti-Vietnam War and anti-draft matters, including newsletters from the Brooklyn-based organizations End the Draft and Committee for Peace Organization. The collection also includes photocopies of New York City Police Department reports concerning the activities of CORE and other organizations from the 1960s and early 1970s.
Finally, the collection includes a selection of books and pamphlets from Arnie Goldwag's library and lapel pins and buttons from election campaigns, anti-war demonstrations, union activities, etc. collected by Goldwag.
Alliance for Jobs or Income Now (New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn Civil Rights Defense Committee (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Congress of Racial Equality. Brooklyn Chapter.; Congress of Racial Equality.; Freedom & Peace Party of New York State.; Goldwag, Arnold; Harlem Parents Committee.; Lynn, Conrad J.; Metropolitan Council on Housing (New York, N.Y.).; Mitchell, David Henry; New York World's Fair (1964-1965).; Owens, Major R., (Major Robert Odell); Peace and Freedom Party (U.S.).; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.).; Youth Against War & Fascism.; African Americans |x Civil rights |z New York (State) |z New York; African Americans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; African Americans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; African Americans |z New York (State) |z New York; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Books; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |v Archival resources.; buttons (information artifacts); Children's rights report; Civil disobedience |z New York (State) |z New York; Civil rights demonstrations |z New York (State) |z New York; Civil rights movements |z New York (State) |z New York; Civil rights workers |z New York (State) |z New York; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; De facto school segregation |z New York (State) |z New York; Discrimination in employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z New York; Discrimination in public accommodations |z Maryland |z Cambridge; Downdraft; Ergo (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Fliers (printed matter); Government, Resistance to |z New York (State) |z New York; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); lapel pins; leaflet (printed work); March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom, Washington, D.C., 1963; Minorities |x Civil rights |z New York (State) |z New York; New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) |x History |v Archival resources; Pamphlets; Photocopies; Photographs; Police patrol |x Surveillance operations; Press releases; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Rent strikes |z New York (State) |z New York; Reunions; Tenants' associations |z New York (State) |z New York
- Series 1: Subject Files, 1950-2007; 7.25 Linear feet
  Arrangement note
  Overall series arrangement
  Arnie Goldwag's files were in no overall order when accessioned by BHS. Accordingly, the arrangement of this series was imposed by the archivist. The arrangement is roughly thematic and chronological.
  The series opens with files that focus principally on CORE actions from 1961-1965, which was the period of Goldwag's main involvement with the organization. These files move from actions concerning local New York City area matters (e.g., local discrimination in housing, employment, education, etc.) to actions with a national orientation (e.g., support for civil rights in the South). Following the files that tend to have a focus on particular actions are those that hold newsletters, clippings, and other material concerned with various CORE and Brooklyn CORE matters.
  Following the CORE-oriented segment is a small number of folders that relate to other activist organizations and subjects dating from the 1960s and 1970s. Following these are photocopies of New York City police reports on demonstrations and other actions by various groups, including CORE, from throughout the 1960s.
  The series then turns to files that have an emphasis on Goldwag himself, including matters concerning his education at Brooklyn College, imprisonment at Rikers Island penitentiary, and other matters at the intersection of his activism and his personal life. The series closes with files dating from the 1980s-2000s that concern reunions, memorials, reminiscences, research papers, and other reflections on CORE, the civil rights struggle, and its continuing legacy.
  As sharp as these dividing lines might appear, the researcher should be aware that there is a fair amount of overlapping material throughout the series so the arrangement described here should not be taken as rigid.
  Folder content and descriptions
  Although Goldwag's files were in no overall order, the bulk of the material was found in folders as labeled by Goldwag. All folder descriptions used by Goldwag were transcribed by the archivist to new archival folders and, with minor exception, content was left in the folder as Goldwag had it. To the extent that the archivist added clarifications to Goldwag's descriptions, these clarifications were shown in [brackets]. Non-substantive changes to labels (e.g., the original "Imp Assoc" rendered by the archivist as "Improvement Association") were not bracketed. Also shown in [brackets] were folder descriptions assigned by the archivist to material found in unlabeled folders or as loose material. Material found loose or in unlabeled folders was not combined by the archivist with materials on the same or similar topic from a Goldwag-labeled folder.
  Some of Goldwag's folder descriptions included date ranges, and these were transcribed by the archivist to the new folders. However, these dates often were not entirely consistent with the folder's contents. Accordingly, the archivist also noted on all folders, below the description, the date range observed during processing; only the observed date range is included in the finding aid's container list.
  Generally, the archivist discarded Goldwag's original folders because of their poor condition. However, in some instances the original folders had notations other than the label written on them. For these, either the original folder was retained within the new archival folder or, more commonly because of the poor condition of the original, a photocopy of the notation was retained.
  Many of the folders contained newspaper clippings or other documents that had been taped or glued to paper backing that had contextual information (e.g., dates) written on it by Goldwag. Because the document had fallen away from the backing over time, the archivist photocopied the two documents together to show their original relationship. Generally in the case of text-only clippings, the originals were then discarded. Any photocopies made by the archivist and placed in the collection were noted as such in [brackets] on the copy; the notation [CPBA] found on many copies is an acronym for "clipping photocopied by archivist." Photocopies with no bracketed annotations were in the original Goldwag material.
  Scope and Contents
  Subject Files principally includes correspondence, newsletters, event announcements (e.g., fliers), directions to demonstrators, photographs, press releases, clippings, and other documents related to Brooklyn CORE's civil rights activism, particularly for the period 1961-1965. The documents in the series reflect actions on a number of fronts. Protests over garbage (Operation Clean Sweep), apartment/housing conditions, traffic, police brutality, and other problems facing the local community are well-represented, especially for the Bedford-Stuyvesant section of Brooklyn. Actions confronting employment discrimination are included, such as those involving Sealtest, Schaefer, White Castle, construction jobs at Downstate Medical Center, and Ebinger Baking; a copy of the signed agreement with Ebinger Baking concerning hiring of African-Americans and Puerto Ricans is in the series.
  The series includes much on protests against de facto school segregation, including actions such as Operation Shutdown and Elaine and Jerome Bibuld's efforts to move their children from an underperforming minority-majority school to a more effective school. The series includes material on the Stall-In, Brooklyn CORE's well-publicized plan to back up traffic at the opening of the 1964 World's Fair as a protest against employment and other forms of discrimination.
  Brooklyn CORE's response to national events is also documented. Responses included participation in the 1962 Freedom Highways program (CORE's challenge to segregated facilities), Operation Federal Intervention in Georgia (FIG), and the March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom. Local actions, including a call for a Christmas shopping boycott, in response to the church bombing and murder of children in Birmingham are represented. Letters written to editors and others protesting cultural imagery/representations of African-Americans in the press, comic strips, etc. are in the series.
  In addition to Brooklyn CORE, other New York-area CORE chapters and organizations, such as the Harlem Parents Committee and the Metropolitan Council on Housing, were involved in the actions of the early 1960s, and the series includes documents related to them as well. Documents from national CORE, such as committee minutes, and national groups, especially the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), are included to a limited extent in the series.
  The series also includes files that illuminate the human dimensions of civil rights activism, in the person of Arnie Goldwag. The series includes Goldwag's files of his activism at Brooklyn College in the late 1950s, his mid-1960s readmission and graduation, his selective service (draft) card, draft induction notice, and record of arrests principally during various civil rights actions. The series includes correspondence sent to Goldwag while he was in Rikers Island penitentiary and his reflections on CORE while in prison, as well as other correspondence to Goldwag from friends and family.
  The focus of Subject Files on CORE actions centers on the first half of the 1960s; there is little material on CORE actions from later periods. Nevertheless, other local organizations continue to be represented through the 1960s, especially Vietnam War opposition/peace organizations such as End the Draft (ETD) and Committee for Peace Organization (CPO). Several of ETD's newsletter, downdraft, and CPO's newsletter, ergo, are in the series. Many documents relate to the military draft refusal trial of David Henry Mitchell, including End the Draft's downdraft commentary. Mitchell's lawyer was Conrad J. Lynn, the African-American civil rights attorney; Lynn also represented Goldwag in at least some of his legal matters, so documents prepared by Lynn on Goldwag's behalf are in the series. Nonetheless, with some exceptions, such as material related to Major Owens's 1986 congressional campaign, the series holds very little material from the 1970s and 1980s. Picking up in the 1990s and 2000s, the series includes memorials, tributes, obituaries, reminiscences, historical research papers, interviews, reunions, and other such material as Goldwag and other former CORE activists reflected back on their 1960s activism.
  The series also holds many photocopies of police reports, notably from the New York City Bureau of Special Services, concerning protests, demonstrations, meetings, and other events held by CORE and other organizations in New York throughout the 1960s and into the early 1970s. These were presumably obtained by Goldwag in the 1990s or later in response to disclosure requests; a copy of at least one such request from Goldwag is in the series. Finally, the series holds a variety of lapel pins and buttons from election campaigns, anti-war demonstrations, union activities, and other matters.
  - Housing Sit-Ins (Misc), Etc., 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Whitings - Housing, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn, Etc. Rent Strikes; Rent Control, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rent Strike, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Garbage [Bed-Stuy], 1950, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Traffic - Bed-Stuy, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Community Problems - Misc, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Employment Misc, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ebingers [Employment], 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - White Castle - Bronx, Brooklyn, N.J., 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [Mayor's Action Panel - Union Hiring Recommendations], 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Flower and Fifth, Beth-El, Bronxville [Hospitals], 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Harlem Hospital, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Downstate Medical Center [and other actions] - Lists, Etc. (3 folders), 1963-2003 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
  - Civil Liberties, Religious Freedom, Academic Freedom, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Jones Beach (L.I. CORE), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Long Beach (L.I. CORE), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Board of Ed - [Elizabeth] Weeks, [Leonard] Morris, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Board of Ed - Bibuld - Leaflets, Etc., 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Board of Ed - Bibuld, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Board of Ed - Sit-Ins (Dec 16 and 30), 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - [School] Boycott (Sept 9, 1963 and Feb 3, 1964), and 275 [Junior High School Integration], 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - [School] Boycott #2 (March 16), 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Schools - Misc Including PAT, Picketing, Etc., 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Operation Shutdown, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Imagery, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Misc Brutality Cases - NYC Police Dept, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Morris Lewis [Shot by Police, Brooklyn], 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - CORE Picketing Etc. of Police Dept, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Riots - Harlem, Philadelphia, Bedford-Stuyvesant, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Independent Community Improvement Assoc - 125th St Boycott, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - [Correspondence re: CORE Actions], 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 7)